<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A light to the longitude, or, The use of an instrument called the seaman's director speedily resolving all astronomical cases and questions concerning the sun, moon, and stars : with several propositions whereby sea-men may find at what meridian and longitude they are at in all parts of the world : published for the advance of navigation / by Robert Theaker.</title>
            <author>Theaker, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12626352</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12626352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A light to the longitude, or, The use of an instrument called the seaman's director speedily resolving all astronomical cases and questions concerning the sun, moon, and stars : with several propositions whereby sea-men may find at what meridian and longitude they are at in all parts of the world : published for the advance of navigation / by Robert Theaker.</title>
                  <author>Theaker, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid for William Fisher ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, June 28, 1665. Roger L'Estrange"</note>
                  <note>The table of contents and the epistle ([4] p.) are bound and photographed between pages 30 and 31.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A LIGHT to the LONGITVDE:</hi> OR The Uſe of an INSTRUMENT <hi>CALLED The SEAMAN'S DIRECTOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SPEEDILY Reſolving all <hi>Aſtronomical</hi> Caſes and Queſtions Concerning the <hi>SUN, MOON,</hi> and <hi>STARS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> Several <hi>Propoſitions</hi> whereby <hi>Sea-men</hi> may find at what <hi>Meridian</hi> and <hi>Longitude</hi> they are at, in all Parts of the WORLD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for the Advance of NAVIGATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Theaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LICENSED,</hi> June 28. 1665.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid</hi> for <hi>William Fiſher</hi> at the <hi>Poſtern-Gate</hi> neer <hi>Tower-Hill.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:18"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Deſcription of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Moving-Sphere or Plain, repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>Having the day of the Month known. To find the Sun's Declination, his place, Sign, and Degree in the Ecliptick, and his right Aſcenſion in Degrees and Minutes or in Hours and Minutes. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>The Sun's place in the Ecliptick being known, to find the Hour and Minute of the Sun's Riſing or Setting any day of the Year. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>To find any fixed Stars Declination, right Aſcenſion in Degrees and Minutes, or in Hours and Minutes, his place, Sign, and Degree, or Longitude in the Ecliptick, and day of the Month belonging to that Star. <hi>p.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>To find, every day in the Year, when any of the fixed Stars comes to the South. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>To find, every day in the Year, when any of the fixed Stars Riſeth or Setteth. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>To find the Sun's Riſing or Setting the ſame way as you find the Stars Riſing or Setting. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>To find the Sun's Altitude, every day of the year, when he comes to the Meridian. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</item>
               <item>To find, every day, how many Degrees the Sun or Stars dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth or goeth under the Horizon at Midnight; Alſo to find the Amplitude of the Sun or Stars, every day in the year, at their Riſing or Setting. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>To find at all times when the North Star is directly South above the Pole, or North under the Pole. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</item>
               <item>To Draw the Parallels of the Sun or Stars Declinations, and thereby to know when they Riſe or Set, or whether they Riſe or Set at all. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64660:19"/>
               <item>To find, every Day in the year, at what time any of the Planets cometh to the South. <hi>p.</hi> 18.</item>
               <item>To find the true Diſtance of the Moon's Motion from the Sun. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>To find the longitude, by knowing when any of the fixed Stars cometh to the South. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</item>
               <item>To find exactly the True Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London. p.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>The firſt of <hi>April,</hi> I demand how the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> may be found and diſcovered, by this Inſtrument. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> at the Sun's Setting. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> at the Sun's Riſing. <hi>p.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> by the Moon when ſhe cometh to the South. <hi>p.</hi> 26.</item>
               <item>To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> by the Moon when ſhe cometh to the South. <hi>p.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item>Two ſeveral Queſtions by finding the Moon South to know what Meridian you are at. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>The firſt Queſtion. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Rule and reaſon for turning the upper Sphere is from 360 degrees. <hi>p.</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>To cut the Horizons for all Latitudes. <hi>p.</hi> 32.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:19"/>
            <head>To the <hi>KING</hi>'s moſt excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dread Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe following endevours ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been brought firſt of all before Your Sacred Majeſty, who did not then deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, but out of Your Princely Favour granted Acceſs, and had the patience to hear the Reaſons and Objections; Your Heroick Breaſt being truly inſpired and perſuaded, that the greateſt Myſteries and Matters in the world, were firſt made known and diſcovered by plain men, and hid from the Learned; and ſo to this day the greateſt pretended natural knowledges are ſtill over-ruled by practical Proof-pieces; upon which conſiderations Your Majeſties faithful Subjects <hi>Robert Theaker</hi> and <hi>Charles Saltonſtall,</hi> after much expences of money and time, are now endevouring to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able all practical Sea-men, with the full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of this Inſtrument; and in regard <hi>Charles Saltonſtall</hi> hath made ſeveral long Voyages and
<pb facs="tcp:64660:20"/> Diſcoveries, inſtructed and brought up a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of expert Navigators, (many of them being now in your Majeſties Service) it is hoped in time he will alſo enable them with this knowledg, that their Proof-pieces may give an end to all Objections: In which hope for the preſent I humbly lay all down at Your Majeſties Feet, beſeeching a favourable acceptance of this Mite, which may prove more worth than the offerings of abundance. And ſo in all obedience I ſubmit my ſelf to Your Majeſties Princely good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, deſiring the great God of Heaven and Earth to grant Your Majeſty a long, proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and happy Reign.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your MAJESTIES moſt humble and obedient Subject and Servant, Robert Theaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving for many years taken diligent notice of the Diurnal Motions of the Heavens, and how the Sun, Moon, and Stars did daily paſs, and appear to be South once in 24 hours, at all the reſpective Meridians in the world. I did apprehend that there might be contrived an Inſtrument which would readily diſtinguiſh to all men at what perticular Meridian and Longitude they were at in all parts: And ſo did at laſt after many alterations and examinations complete this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, now called, <hi>A Light to the Longitude;</hi> which doth in a plain and facil way ſpeedily Anſwer all Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Propoſitions concerning the Sun, Moon, and Stars, only by turning the upper Plain repreſenting the Heavens or Terreſtrial Globe, without the knowledge of the doctrine of Spherical Triangles, which many men did never attain to: Alſo by frequent practice and a little Inſtruction in uſing this Inſtrument, all the Conſtellations and fixed Stars in the heavens are readily found out and known in all places at any hour of the Night, very helpful to practical Seamen in the Art of Navigation, and being joyned with the true nature and way of the turning this Inſtrument, I ſuppoſe they will ſpeedily find at what particular Meridian they are
<pb facs="tcp:64660:3"/> at, which is indeed true <hi>Aſtronomical, Geographical,</hi> and <hi>Hydrographical</hi> Longitude, and is not the meaſuring of Diſtances betwixt any two Meridians by <hi>Pendulums, Sand-glaſſes, Water-glaſſes,</hi> &amp;c. but offereth to find under which of the 360 Meridians all Iſlands, Head lands, Main-Lands, Cities and Towns are truly Situated and Placec, againſt which there hath been much oppoſition en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to darken and put out this <hi>Light to the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:</hi> But there was a perſon (very well known to moſt Navigators) which ſtood in the Gap, and defended it from being quite extinguiſhed, whoſe further Study and endevours I doubt not but will daily add more and more Light to this matter, until at laſt practical Sea-men gain the honour, and bring home their undeniable Proof-pieces, and put an end to all Objections; And ſo for preſent I leave all my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours to your favourable Conſtruction, hoping they will prove worthy of your Acceptance, and in time beneficial to all men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend Ro. Theaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>IF there be any one that deſireth to be more fully inſtructed in the uſe of this Inſtrument, they may repair unto <hi>Charles Saltonſtall</hi> Publick Profeſſor and Teacher of the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> living neer the <hi>Poſtern-gate</hi> on <hi>Eaſt-Tower-hill,</hi> who will ſatisfie their deſires.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64660:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The full Deſcription of an Inſtrument lately In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by</hi> Robert Theaker, <hi>but now upon his requeſt explained, and the manifold <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes thereof written for the general good, by</hi> Charles Saltonſtal, <hi>Profeſſor and Practitioner of the Mathematick, neer the</hi> Poſtern-gate <hi>on</hi> Eaſt-Tower-hill.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Inſtrument conſiſteth of two Plains, the lowermoſt repreſenteth the Terreſtrial Globe, and ſtandeth fix'd, and is not to be removed at all, and thereupon is delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and drawn three diſtinct hour Circles; the outwardmoſt Circle is divided into 24 Hours, ending at <hi>♈ Aries,</hi> and numbred into the Eaſt with 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until the whole Circle be counted round about to 24 hours ending again at <hi>♈ Aries</hi> where it firſt began. In this hour Circleis reckoned the right Aſcenſion of the Sun ot fixed Stars, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to time, or in Hours and Minutes; The next, or ſecond hour Circle I call <hi>♈ Aries hour-Circle,</hi> becauſe <hi>♈ Aries</hi> ſtands there betwixt 24 hours in the outward hour-Circle, and 12 hours in the inward or third hour-Circle, and this hour-Circle is numbred from 12. of the Clock at Noon the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> into the Weſt, with 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 12 of the Clock at Night; and from thence back again with 1, 2, 3 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 12. of the Clock at Noon the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> where it firſt began; now in this hour-Circle is reckoned the time of Sun-Riſing or Setting, the hour of any fixed Stars Riſing or Setting, and coming to the Sorth,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64660:4"/> as hereafter in the uſe of this Inſtrument will more evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; The third hour-Circle beginneth at <hi>♈ Aries</hi> with 12 of the Clock the beginning and ending of all Longitude in the Equinoctial, where is alſo placed 360 degrees, and is numbred into the Weſt with 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 12 of the Clock, and from thence back again with 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 12 of the Clock where it firſt began, <hi>♈ Aries;</hi> In this Circle is reckoned the difference of time, as hereafter will amply appear; The next and innermoſt Circle drawn upon this fixed Plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe is the Equinoctial beginning and ending at <hi>♈ Aries</hi> with 360 degrees, Numbred into the Eaſt with 10, 20, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until it be counted round about, and then concludeth again with 360 degrees where it firſt began, the beginning and ending of all Longitude upon the Earth; Then upon this lower fixed plain repreſenting the Terreſtial Globe, there are drawn at every tenth degree from the Equinoctial, ſtraight Lines, all meeting in the Centre, which is here in this Projection counted the Pole of the World; then from that Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre or Pole, at every ten degrees Latitude or Breadth from the Equinoctial, there is drawn a Concentrick Circle, which are numbred by Tens from the Equinoctial in this manner, 10, 20, 30, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concluding with 90 degrees in the Centre, or Pole, all graduated upon a moving Meridian turning about in the Centre, which is here counted the Pole of the World, by which means the Latitude of all places upon the Terreſtial Globe are readily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and made known; Then there are alſo two ſmall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors repreſented containing the 32 points of the Compaſs upon this fixed Plain, which may be made of Braſs, Horn, or Paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board at pleaſure, by which means all Courſes and Bearings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt place and place according to the Terreſtrial Globe, thus <hi>projected in Plano,</hi> wherein you may readily find the Latitude, Longitude, Courſe, and Diſtance, betwixt any two places how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſituated upon the Terreſtrial Globe: And by the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the upper Moving or Turning Plain repreſenting the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Globe, many excellent Matters, Operations and Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> are readily performed, and plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated according to the Motions of the Heavens, as will be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after amply manifeſted.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64660:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Deſcription of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Moving-Sphere or Plain, repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe.</head>
               <p>IN this Upper Moving Plain or Sphere, upon the outward edg there is drawn the Circle of Months numbred by tens, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Diurnal Motion, placing alwayes the tenth day of <hi>March</hi> at ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> by which means you may there find any day of the year you deſire, and ſo know the exact time of the Sun or Stars Riſing, Setting, and coming to the South, as hereafter will am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply appear: The next and innermoſt Circle deſcribed upon that uppermoſt Moving Plain, or Sphere, is the Equinoctial Circle Numbred by 10 degrees, 20, 30, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into the Eaſt, until you count round about to ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> again, and there end and finiſh with 360 degrees, where you firſt began, in the ſame manner as the Equinoctial is numbred and deſcribed on the lower fixed Plain; And from this Equinoctial is reckoned the Sun or Stars Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon another moving Meridian called an <hi>Index,</hi> placed and turned about in the Centre of this upper moving-Plain, as hereafter in uſe will facilly appear; Then upon this upper Moving Sphere or Plain there is deſcribed the Ecliptick Circle, being the path-way of the Sun, and is numbred from ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the Northern Signs with 10 degrees, 20 degrees, and then 30 degrees, and then beginning again from ♉ with 10 degr. 20 degr. &amp; then 30 degr. and ſo in the ſame manner numbring again from ♊ <hi>Gemini</hi> 10 degrees, 20 degrees, and 30 degrees to ♋ <hi>Cancer,</hi> attributing and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to each Sign 30 degrees; and ſo in the ſame manner are the Southern Signs numbred, beginning from ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> with 10 degrees, 20 degrees, and then 30 degrees; and then beginning again from ♏ <hi>Scorpio,</hi> with 10 degrees, 20 degrees, and then 30 degrees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> reckoning ſtill on in the ſame manner, until you have coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted round about and return again to ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> where you firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; keeping the ſame order as you did in the Northern Signes, allowing 30 degrees to each Sign; And on this Moving Plain there is alſo a ſmaller Circle deſcribed repreſenting the Tropicks of ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> and ♑ <hi>Capricorn</hi> touching the Ecliptick in the firſt minute of ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> and ♑ <hi>Capricorn; Cancer</hi> ſhewing that the Sun's greateſt Declination North, is 23 degrees 30 Minutes; and ♑
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64660:5"/> 
                  <hi>Capricorn</hi> ſheweth the Sun's greateſt declinations South is alſo 23 degrees and 30 minutes, the Tropicks only ſhewing the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points in the Ecliptick, as the word ſignifies, declaring and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bounds to the Sun's greateſt Declinations North or South, not to exceed 23 degrees, 30 minutes, but muſt then turn back again. There is alſo belonging to this moving Plain, repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe, a Moving Meridian I call an <hi>Index,</hi> graduated both wayes from the Equinoctial, numbred with 10 degrees, 20, 30, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concluding with 90 degrees in the Centre or Pole of the World, and the whole graduated Moving Meridian is exactly in length equal to the Diameter of the Equinoctial deſcribed on that upper Moving Plain, and the other parts of this Moving Meridian or <hi>Index,</hi> which are beyond or without the Graduated parts, ſerveth to cut the Circle of Months, the hour-Circles and Equinoctial deſcribed, on the fixed or lower Plain, as the Caſe ſhal require. Laſtly, there is placed upon this Upper Sphere or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Plain, a Turning Horizon in the Centre, being to draw all Pannoles thereupon, and may be fitted for any Latitude required, having two <hi>Indexes</hi> thereunto belonging, the Longer <hi>Index</hi> to be applied for the Riſing or Setting of the Sun, when he is in the Northern Signs: or for the Southing, Riſing, and Setting of the Northern Stars, and the ſhorter <hi>Index</hi> is to be applied to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian for the Riſing, Setting, and Southing the Southern Stars, or for the Sun when the Sun is in the Southern Signs. Theſe are all the parts of this Inſtrument deſcribed on the lower fixed Plain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Terreſtrial Globe; as alſo the Moving Upper Sphere, or Plain, repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe, which being well underſtood, and rightly applyed, will perform many excellent things in <hi>Navigation</hi> and <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64660:5"/>
               <head>Having the day of the Month known. To find the Sun's Declination, his place Sign, and Degree in the Ecliptick, and his right Aſcenſion in Degrees and Minutes or in Hours and Minutes.</head>
               <p>THeſe propoſitions are all readily wrought by this Inſtrument by the Circles deſcribed on the uppermoſt plain repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe, and by the outwardmoſt hour-Circle in the lower plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe, between the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial and the Center which is the Pole of the World: firſt then I ſay, turn the uppermoſt Sphere, being the Celeſtial Globe, untill ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> there agree with ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the lowermoſt Shere repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Terreſtrial Globe, then bring the moving Meridian or Index to the day of the Moneth wherein you deſire to know any of theſe ſeveral propoſitions, and you will then find that the diſtance at that time in the upper plain betwixt the Equinoctial &amp; the Ecliptick, reckoned in the moving Meridian or Index, is the Sun's declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the point or place cut in the Ecliptick at the ſame time by the ſame moving Meridian or Index, ſheweth the Sign, Degree, and Minute that the Sun is in at that time. And the Degree and Minute then cut in the Equinoctial, by the ſame move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Meridian or Index, ſheweth the Sun's right Aſcenſion in Degrees and Minutes, and then in the outwardmoſt Hour-Circle on the lower plain the ſame moving Meridian or Index ſheweth the Sun's right Aſcenſion in time or Hours and Minutes. So the 23d day of <hi>February</hi> you will find by this Inſtrument that the Sun hath 6 Degrees South declination, his place and Sign in the Ecliptick 15 Degrees of ♓ <hi>Piſces</hi> one of the Southern Signs, his right Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Degrees 346 Degrees, whoſe complement to a whole Circle is 14 Degrees, the diſtance from ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> the next Equinoctial point, and the time of the Sun's right Aſcenſion is in Hours and Minutes 23-4, and the complement from ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in time is 56 Minutes.</p>
               <p>So in the ſame manner, the 20th day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> if you deſire to know the Sun's Declination, his place, Sign, and Degree in the Ecliptick, his right Aſcenſion, in Degrees and Minutes, as alſo in Hours and Minutes; fix this Inſtrument in all reſpects as before,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64660:6"/> making ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the upper plain and ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the lower plain to ſtand right againſt each other, and then bring the moving Meridian or Index to the 20th day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> and you will then find the Suns declination is 15 degrees North, his place in the Ecliptick 10-8 Degrees eight Minuts of ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> his right Aſcenſion in Degrees from <hi>Aries;</hi> the next Equinoctial point is 38 degrees, which in time is 2-32 Hours thirty two Minutes, as appeareth in the outwardmoſt hour-Circle in the lower plain, where the moving Meridian cutteth,</p>
               <p>So the 31day of <hi>May</hi> you will find the Sun's declination 23-10 Degrees and ten Minutes North, his place in the Ecliptick 19-50 nineteen Degrees and 50 Minuts of ♊ <hi>Gemini,</hi> his right Aſcenſion 78 Degrees from ♈ which in time is 5-12 Hours and twelve Minutes, as appeareth in the lowermoſt outward hour Circle, and ſo in the ſame manner all ſorts of propoſitions of the like Nature.</p>
               <p>Note all theſe five propoſitions: that is to ſay, the Sun's decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Sun's place, the Degree and Sign, which the Sun is in every day, the Sun's right Aſcenſion in Degrees, the Sun's right Aſcenſion in Hours, and Minutes, are all anſwered at one opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, only by bringing the moving Meridian or Index to the day of the Moneth, which is an exceeding great diſpatch, and will prove very profitable in Aſtronomical practices.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sun's place in the Ecliptick being known, to find the Hour and Minute of the Sun's Riſing or Setting any day of the Year.</head>
               <p>THe Sun's place being found by this Inſtrument, as hath been formerly taught; bring the longeſt Index of the Horizontal plain having nothing but the pannage there on graduated unto 12 a clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, the ſame Index then cutting 20 Degrees of longitude in the lowermoſt plain, the longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and there keep that Horizontal Index faſt, and then turn the upper moving plain, repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe, untill the place of the Sun in the Ecliptick come exactly to the plain Horizon, at which edg inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecting or touch point
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64660:6"/> keep the Ecliptick farſt, and then bring the moving Meridian or Index to that interſection, made by the meeting of the Sun in that point in the Horizon, and then at that time in the Eaſt Hemiſphere in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, you will find the moving Meridian doth there cut the Hour and Minute of Sun riſing, and in the Weſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere, the other end of the moving Meridian in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle doth at the ſame time ſhew the Hour and Minute of Sun Setting; alſo at the ſame time the moving Meridian will ſhew the Sun's declination in the moving Meridian and day of the Month in the Circle of daies and Months, whether the Sun be either in any of the Northern Signs or Southern Signs.</p>
               <p>So the Sun being in the firſt Minute of ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> bring the longeſt Index of the Horizon to 12 Hours and 20 Degrees in the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fixed plain, and there keep that Index faſt; then turn about the upper moving Sphere untill the firſt Minute of ♉ <hi>Taurus</hi> in the Ecliptick interſect, touch or joyneth with the edge of the plain Horizon, and there hold all faſt together, and then bring the move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Meridian or Index to that point or interſection in the Horizon, &amp; one end in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour Circle in the Eaſt Hemiſphere will ſhew the Sun Riſeth then at 5 a clock in the Morning; and the other end at the ſame time in the Weſt Semicircle of the Sphere in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle will ſhew the Sun then Setteth at 7 a clock in the Afternoon. Note when you would know the time of Sun Riſing, you muſt count the hour from 12 in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle backwards calling 11one, 10 two, 9 three 8 four, 7 five, 6 ſix, 5 ſeven <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or having the hour of Sun Setting if you ſubſtract that from 12, there will reſt the hour of Sun Riſing: ſo if the Sun Riſeth at 5 that ſubſtracted from 12 reſteth 7 a clock for Sun Setting, or if the Sun Setteth at 7 a clock that ſubſtracted from 12 reſteth 5 hours for the time of Sun Riſing. Alſo now at the ſame time that end of the moving Meridian or Index which cuts the Sun's place brought to the Horizon in the Circle of daies and months, will ſhew that it is now the 10th day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> and that the Sun hath now 11 Degrees and 35 minuts North declination accounted in the moving Meridian or Index.</p>
               <p>So in the ſame manner the 20 day of <hi>October,</hi> the Sun being then in the 7 Degree of ♏ <hi>Scorpio,</hi> by this Inſtrument, as hath been formerly taught, you will find the Sun Riſeth at 7 a clock 13 minuts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64660:7"/> paſt in the morning and Setteth at 4 a clock 47 minutes paſt in the Afternoon: and in the Circle of Months the moving Meridian will ſhew then that it is the 20 day of <hi>October,</hi> and at the ſame time on the moving Meridian or Index you will ſee the Sun hath 14 Degrees South declination; and ſo in the ſame manner you may find all theſe ſeveral propoſitions: the Sun being in any Sign and Degree in the Ecliptick, in all which you may facilly perceive, very great expedition and diſpatch, which will prove very uſefull to all practical Sea-men, and ſuch as have occaſion to inquire into theſe Aſtronomical caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find any fixed Stars Declination, right Aſcenſion in Degrees and Minutes, or in Hours and Minutes, his place, Sign, and Degree, or Longitude in the Ecliptick, and day of the Month belonging to that Star.</head>
               <p>THeſe propoſitions are all readily wrought by this Inſtrument, by the application of the great Circles, deſcribed on the uppermoſt moving Sphere or plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe, and by the moving Meridian or Index thereon placed, with the help of the outwardmoſt hour-Circle placed on the lower fixed plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe; for if you turn the upper plain untill ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in that plain agree or point directly with ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the lower fixed plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe, and there hold it faſt, and then bring the moving Meridian or Index to that Star whereof you deſire to know the declination, right Aſcenſion in Degrees or Time, his place and Degree or longitude in the Ecliptick, with the day of the Month belonging to that Star, and there alſo hold that moving Meridian faſt; and you will then find in the moving Meridian that the diſtance betwixt the Equinoctial and the Star is his declination, the Degrees cut in the Equinoctial his right Aſcenſion in Degrees, and the hour cut by the ſame moving Meridian or Index at the ſame time in the outwardmoſt hour-Circle upon the lowermoſt fixed plain ſheweth his right Aſcenſion in hours and minutes; alſo at the ſame time this moving Meridian or Index doth then cut in the Ecliptick the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64660:7"/> place, Sign, Degree, and longitude of that Star: and laſtly, this moving Meridian doth then ſhew in the Circle of months the day of that month belonging to that Star wherein all theſe Aſtronomical effects, caſes, and concluſions come to paſs.</p>
               <p>So if you deſire at any time to know the declination, right Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Degrees and Time, the place, Sign, Degree, and longitude of the fixed Star called <hi>Orion's</hi> left ſhoulder: Firſt turn the upper plain untill ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in that moving plain be right againſt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the lower fixed plain, and there keep them together, then bring the moving Meridian or Index unto the Star called <hi>Orion's</hi> left ſhoulder, and there alſo ſtay and hold faſt that moving Meridian, and then you will readily find the diſtance between that Star and the Equinoctial reckoned in the moving Meridian is 6 Degrees, which is his declination, North; and the ſame moving Meridian will then at the ſame time cut 77 Degrees in the Equinoctial, which is his right Aſcenſion in Degrees, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o at the ſame time cutteth in the outward hour Circle on the fixed plain 5 hours and 8 minutes, which is his right Aſcenſion in time; and in the Ecliptick the ſame moving Meridian at the ſame time cutteth 18 of ♊ <hi>Gemini</hi> which is his place or longitude; and laſtly, the ſame Index at the ſame time in the Circle of Months ſheweth that it is the 29th day of <hi>May,</hi> all which by this Inſtrument is apparently manifeſted at one and the ſame time, which is a notable diſpatch, and worthy of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. So again in the ſame manner, if you deſire to find all theſe Aſtronomical propoſitions concerning the Star called the <hi>Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dog,</hi> move as before the upper plain untill ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> there ſtand right againſt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the lower fixed plain, then bring the moving. <hi>Meridian</hi> or Index to the Star called the <hi>Great Dog,</hi> and you find the diſtance betwixt that Star and the Equinoctial reckoned in the moving Merridian, is 16 Degrees 32 minutes, which is his declination South, and at the ſame time this moving Meridian in the Equinoctial ſheweth his right Aſcenſion is 98 Degrees, and in the outward hour-Circle in the fixed plain ſheweth 6 hours 32 minutes is the <hi>Great Dog's</hi> right Aſcenſion in time and then laſtly cuts in the Ecliptick 7 Degrees of ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> which is the <hi>Great Dog's</hi> place or longitude, and in the Circle of Months 17 day 2 minuts of <hi>June,</hi> and ſo of all other Stars whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64660:8"/>
               <head>To find, every day in the Year, when any of the fixed Stars comes to the South.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, bring the moving Meridian or Index to 12 hours in the lower fixed plain in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, then the ſame Index at the ſame time will alſo cut 20 Degrees in the Equinoctial, deſcribed on the lower fixed plain, which is in this projection accounted the longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and there keeping the moving Meridian faſt, turn the upper plain repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe untill the moving Meridian alſo cut the Starr which you deſire to know at what time it comes to be South, and there keep the Star faſt, and then turn the moving Index or Meridian to the day of any Month, and in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle the ſame moving Meridian will ſhew the hour when that Star cometh to the South.</p>
               <p>So the Star called the <hi>Great Dog</hi> being brought to ſtand right againſt 12 hours and 20 Degrees in the lower fixed plain, and there kept faſt, and then if you turn the moving Index or Meridian to the firſt day of <hi>January,</hi> the ſame Index will then ſhew in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle 11 a clock at night at which hour the Star called the <hi>Great Dog</hi> cometh to the South; and if you then keep the Inſtrument unaltred, and turn the ſame moving Meridian to the firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> the Index then in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle will ſhew 3 a clock 24 minuts in the morning, which is the time when the <hi>Great Dog</hi> cometh to the South: and on the firſt day of <hi>December</hi> the Index ſheweth 1 a clock 16 minutes in the morning for the hour when the <hi>Great Dog</hi> cometh to the South.</p>
               <p>So in the ſame manner, if you would know when the Star called <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder</hi> cometh to the South, that Star brought to 12 hours and 20 Degrees in the lowermoſt fixed plain, the longitude of <hi>London</hi> as before, the moving Meridian brought to the firſt day of <hi>January</hi> will ſhew 9 a clock 37 minuts paſt in the afternoon, and then the Star called <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder</hi> cometh to the South.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64660:8"/>
               <head>To find, every day in the Year, when any of the fixed Stars Riſeth or Setteth.</head>
               <p>HEre in this caſe, if it be a Star that hath North declination, bring the longeſt Index of the moving Horizon, to 12 a clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, which will then alſo cut the fixed Equinoctial 20 Degrees, the longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this projection: but if it be a Star that hath South declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then bring the ſhorteſt Index of the moving Horizon, to 12 a clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle and 20 Degrees in the lowerm oſt fixed Equinoctial as before, and there keep the Horizontal Index faſtand turn the upper moving Sphere, or plain repreſenting the Celeſtial Globe, untill the Star, the time of whoſe Riſing you deſire to know come exactly to touch the Circular edge of the moving Horizon in the Eaſt Semicircle of the moving Sphere; or if you deſire to know the time of the Stars ſetting, turn the whole moving Sphere or plain untill the Star come to the Circular edg of the moving Horizon in the Weſt Semicircle of the moving Sphere; I call the Eaſt Semicircle that which is conteined betwixt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> and ♎ <hi>Libra,</hi> the Ecliptick having thereon placed the ſix Northern Signs <hi>viz. ♈ Aries, ♉ Taurus, ♊ Gemini, ♋ Cancer, ♌ Leo, ♍ Virgo,</hi> and in the Circle of months, <hi>Aprill, May, June, July, Auguſt, September;</hi> and the other Semicircle betwixt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> and ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> contein the Southern Signs and the Circle of months, <hi>March, February, January, December, November,</hi> I call the Weſt Semicircle: and in the Eaſt Semicircle I alwaies contein the Sun or Stars Riſing, and in the Weſt the Sun or Stars Setting: now the Star thus ſtated keep all, turn the moving Index or Meridian to the day in the Circle of month wherein you deſire to know the time of that Stars Riſing or ſetting, and the ſame Index at the ſame time will ſhew in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, the time of that Stars Riſing, if the Star touch the Horrizontal edg in the Eaſt Semicircle, or in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, will ſhew the time of the Stars Setting if the Star touch the edg of the moveing Horizon in the Weſt Semicircle of the Spheer.</p>
               <p>So the Star called the <hi>Great Dog,</hi> if you deſire to know the time of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64660:9"/> his Riſing the 10 day of <hi>March,</hi> (being the Star's declination is South) bring the ſhorteſt <hi>Index</hi> of the moving Horizon to 12 of the Clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour Circle, and to 20 degrees in the lower fixed Equinoctial; then keeping that <hi>Index</hi> there faſt, turn the whole moving Sphere or Plain until the Star called the <hi>Great Dog</hi> come exactly to the edg of the Horizon in the Eaſt Semicircle, and then the moving <hi>Index</hi> or Meridian brought to the 10 day of <hi>March,</hi> will ſhew in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, that the <hi>Great Dog</hi> riſeth at 1 of the Clock, 52 minutes in the Afternoon, and ſets at a 11 of the Clock and 8 minutes in the Afternoon, when the Star is at the edg of the Moving Horizon, in the Weſt Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle.</p>
               <p>And after the ſame manner, if you deſire to know when the Star called <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder</hi> riſeth or ſetteth the 10. day of <hi>March;</hi> now becauſe the Star hath North declination, keep the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the moving Horizon on 12 of the Clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour Circle, and 20 degrees in the lower fixed Equinoctial as before, then turn the upper Sphere or moving Plain until the Star, called <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder,</hi> come to the edg of the Horizon in the Eaſt Semicircle, and there keeping all faſt, bring the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Meridian to the 10 day of <hi>March,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Index</hi> in <hi>Aries</hi> hour Circle will ſhew that <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder</hi> riſeth at 10 of the Clock and 40 minutes in the morning; and if the ſame Star be brought to the edg of the moving Horizon, in the Weſt Semicircle, and then the moving Meridian brought to the 10. of <hi>March,</hi> the ſame <hi>Index</hi> will ſhew in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle that the <hi>Orion's left ſhoulder</hi> ſets at 11 of the Clock and 40 minutes in the Afternoon: and ſo of all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find the Sun's Riſing or Setting the ſame way as you find the Stars Riſing or Setting.</head>
               <p>FOrmerly it hath been ſhewed, that when the <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon was placed upon the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> at 12 hours and 20 degrees Longitude in the lower fixed Plain, and there kept faſt, then the place of the Sun brought to the Horizon, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64660:9"/> moving Meridian to the day of the Month deſired, one end of that <hi>Index</hi> in the Eaſt Semicircle would then ſhew the time of Sun Riſing, and the other the time of Sun Setting, but the Riſing and Setting of the fixed Stars could not be ſo found; for after the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex</hi> of the Horizon was kept at the Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> then the ſame Star was brought firſt to touch the Eaſt part of the Horizon, and then according to the day propoſed, the moving Meridian did in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle ſhew the time of that Star's Riſing, and then the ſame Star brought again to touch the Weſt part of the Horizon, and the moving Meridian turned to the ſame day in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle ſhewed the time of that Star's Setting; So in the ſame manner, if you pleaſe, you may imploy the place of the Sun to the Eaſt part of the Horizon for his Riſing, and the Weſt part for his Setting; and the moving Meridian brought to the propoſed day, when the Sun is at the Eaſt part of the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, will in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle ſhew the time of Sun Riſing; and on the ſame day, when the Sun cometh to the Weſt part of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, the ſame moving Meridian in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle will ſhew the time of Sun Setting: Provided alwayes if the Sun be in any of the Northern Signs, and ſo hath North declination, then you muſt bring the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon to 12 hours and 20 degrees in the fixed Plain, the Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> and then proceed as before hath been taught: But if the Sun be in the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Signs, and ſo hath South declination, then bring the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon to 12 Hours and 20 degrees, in the lower fixed Plain, the Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to find the Riſing and Setting of the Sun upon the day propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>So the 20 day of <hi>April,</hi> the Sun's place being 10 degrees 12 Minutes of ♉ <hi>Taurus;</hi> now becauſe ♉ <hi>Taurus</hi> is one of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Signs, and ſo the Sun hath North declination, bring the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the moving Horizon to 12 hours 20 degrees in the lower fixed Plain, the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> then bring the Sun's place in the Ecliptick firſt to the Eaſt part of the Horizon, and ſo keep all faſt, and then turn the moving Meridian to the 20 day of <hi>April,</hi> and it will then ſhew in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle that the Sun Riſeth at 4 of the Clock 41 Minutes paſt in the morning, &amp; Setteth at 7 of the Clock 41 minutes paſt in the Afternoon; Or if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64660:10"/> you deſire to know the 20 day of <hi>October,</hi> at what time the Sun Riſeth or Setteth. Now again, becauſe the Sun's place is 7 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ♏ <hi>Scorpio,</hi> one of the Southern Signs, and ſo hath South declination, bring the ſhorteſt <hi>Index</hi> of the moving Horizon to 12 of the Clock and 20 degrees in the lower fixed Plain, and there keep it faſt; and then turn the upper moving Plain, until the Sun's place 7 degrees of ♏ <hi>Scorpio</hi> come to the Eaſt part of the Horizon, and then the moving <hi>Index</hi> brought to the 20 day of <hi>October,</hi> will ſhew the Sun then Riſeth at 7 of the Clock 13 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes paſt in the morning, and ſets at 4 of the Clock 47 minutes paſt in the Afternoon; which is a much better way then to count one end of the Morning <hi>Index</hi> to cut the Hour of Sun ſetting, and the other end counted back from 12 in <hi>Aries</hi> hour Circle for the time of Sun Riſing, as hath been formerly taught; Alſo by this means the whole moving upper Plain repreſenting the celeſtial Globe, being turned about in this Diurnal Motion upon any day required, will ſhew the time of the Sun's Riſing or Setting, and all the Stars Riſing, Setting, and coming to the South in order, from whence in <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> many beneficial concluſions may be readily drawn; Seeing this Inſtrument is ſo exact, and maketh ſuch extraordinary diſpatch anſwering many varieties all at once, which by proportion and the doctrine of Spherical Triangles, will require longer time, notwithſtanding the help of the Logarithmes and Natural Signs provided in our dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find the Sun's Altitude every day of the year when he comes to the Meridian.</head>
               <p>THIS propoſition is very uſeful for all Seamen readily to ſet the ſhadow vein in obſervation at Sea to find the Latitude; Firſt then, if you turn the moving Meridian and ſhorter <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon both together, to ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the moving Plain, the edg of the Horizon will then cut the moving Meridian in 38 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and 30 minutes, the height of the Sun upon the Meridian the 10 day of <hi>March</hi> in the Latitude of 51 degrees and 30 minutes, and is alſo the height of the Equinoctial in that Latitude for ever;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64660:10"/> Therefore at any time, if you add the Sun's declination when it is North, or ſubſtract it when it is South from 38 degrees and 30 minutes, the height of the Equinoctial, it will ſhew the height of the Sun that day upon his Meridian; ſo the 20 day of <hi>April</hi> the Suns Declination is 15 degrees North, which added to the 38 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 30 minutes, ſheweth the Altitude of the Sun that day upon the Meridian is 53 degrees 30 minutes; and the 18 of <hi>October</hi> the Sun hath 13 degrees 30 minutes South declination, which ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from 38 degrees 30 minutes, reſteth 25 degreet, which is the height of the Sun that day upon his Meridian here in the North Latitude of 51 degrees 30 minutes; and ſo of all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find every day how many Degrees the Sun or Stars dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth or goeth under the Horizon at Midnight; Alſo to find the Amplitude of the Sun or Stars every day in the year at their Riſing or Setting.</head>
               <p>TO find the Sun's Amplitude at his riſing or ſetting by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument; there muſt alſo be provided a ſtreight Ruler, to be employed as occaſion ſhall require: Firſt then, when you deſire to know the Sun's Amplitude, you muſt grant the Diameter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> and ♎ <hi>Libra</hi> to repreſent the prime vertical Circle, or Circle of the Eaſt and Weſt, and the Quadrant from ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> to 90 degrees, reckoned in the Equinoctial, the Quadrant of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes and the Diameter, betwixt 90 degrees, and 270 degrees, the Horizon Circle; then having the Latitude of any place, and declination of the Sun, bring the moving Meridian to the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and there keep it faſt, then with a pair of Compaſſes take the declination out of the Equinoctial being one of the great Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and joyn it to the point of Latitude, in the Quadrant of Latitudes towards ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> and then lay a ſtreight Ruler from that point parallel to the moving Meridian, which is held faſt at the point of Latitude, and then obſerve where the Ruler cuts or croſſeth the Diameter now repreſenting the Horizon; and then alſo obſerve under the Horizon where that ſtreight Ruler cutteh the Equinoctial, and ſo many degrees doth the Sun or Star dip or go
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64660:11"/> under the Horizon or Midnight; then from the ſame point in the Horizon, turn or lay the ſtreight Ruler parallel to the prime verti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and then in the Equinoctial, being one of the great Circles, it will cut the true Amplitude of the Sun or Stars, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the diſtance contained betwixt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> and that point ſo cut.</p>
               <p>So in the North Latitude of 51 degrees 30 minutes, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Declination of the Sun being 23 degrees, 30 minutes, if you bring the moving <hi>Index</hi> to 51 degrees 30 minutes in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant of Latitude, and thereunto joyn the Declination 23 degrees and 30 minutes, and then from that point lay a ſtreight Ruler pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to the moving Meridian or <hi>Index,</hi> it will cut under the Horizon in the Equinoctial 15 degrees, and ſo much goeth the Sun then under the Horizon at Midnight; alſo at the ſame time note the place or point cut in the Horizon by the ſame ſtreight Ruler, and then turn or lay the Ruler from that point in the Horizon parallel to the <hi>prime vertical,</hi> and where it cutteth the Equinoctial, the diſtance betwixt ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> and that point is the Amplitude, which here at this time appeareth to be 39 degrees and 50 minutes, being the greateſt Amplitude the Sun can poſſibly have here at <hi>London</hi> in the North Latitude of 51 degrees 30 minutes; And ſo in the ſame manner you may find the Amplitude of any of the fixed Stars at their riſing or ſetting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> If the Sun hath North declination, it is called North Amplitude; and if it hath South declination, it is called South Amplitude, and the greater Latitude the greater Amplitude; and ſo of the fixed Stars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note alſo,</hi> Until the Sun be 18 degrees under the Horizon it is the <hi>Crepuſculum</hi> or Twilight; therefore here at <hi>London</hi> when the Sun hath 23 degrees 30 minutes North declination, the Sun dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth but 15 degrees under the Horizon; Therefore here at <hi>London</hi> at that time, it is not perfect Night at all, but the Twilight con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64660:11"/>
               <head>To find at all Altines when the North Star is directly South above the Pole, or North under the Pole.</head>
               <p>TO know at what hour, every Day and Night, the North Star is directly North or South, above or under the Pole; bring the moving Meridian to 12 of the Clock in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle and 20 degrees, the Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> then turn the upper Plain, until the Star called <hi>Aliot,</hi> being a Star in the <hi>Great Bear's Rumpe,</hi> or the hindmoſt of the 3 in <hi>Charles his Waine,</hi> unto that <hi>Index</hi> on the North or Southſide, and then if that Star be on the South ſide, the North Star is then 2 degrees 30 minutes under the Pole, and if <hi>Aliot</hi> be on the Northſide, the North Star is then 2 degrees 30 minutes above the Pole.</p>
               <p>So the 22 day of <hi>March, Aliot</hi> is South at 12 of the Clock at Night, and ſo the North Star is then 2 degrees 30 minutes under the Pole; and the 4 day of <hi>February, Aliot</hi> is South at 5 of the Clock in the morning, and ſo the North Star is then alſo 2 degrees 30 minutes under the Pole: And the 9 day of <hi>September, Aliot</hi> is North at 12 of the Clock at Night, and the North Star is then 2 degrees 30 minutes above the Pole; And the 25 day of <hi>October, Aliot</hi> is North at 9 of the Clock at Night, and then the North Star is 2 degrees 30 minutes above the Pole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To Draw the Parallels of the Sun or Stars Declinations, and thereby to know when they Riſe or Set, or whether they Riſe or Set at all.</head>
               <p>TO draw the parallels of Declination; Firſt, ſet one Foot of the Compaſſes in the Pole or Centre of the moving Meridian, and then extend the other foot to 5 degrees, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the ſame moving Meridian, according as the Declination may require; then with the ſame extent ſo taken out of the moving Meridian, ſet one foot in the Centre of the moving Horizon, and from the Diameter ſweep an arch of a Circle both wayes to cut
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64660:12"/> the outward edg of that plain Horizon, with points or Croſſings in the edg of the Horizon, are the direct places where thoſe Stars come unto at their riſing or ſetting; <hi>Note,</hi> if any Star here in the Latitude of 51 degrees 30 minutes, hath his Declination North equal or more than the Complement of the Latitude, that Star (I ſay) ſets not at all, for then the Compaſſes in the plain Horizon will ſweep an Arch of a Circle within the plain Horizon, and will not reach the outward edg, therefore that Star ſets not at all; And ſo if any Star hath South declination equal or greater than the Complement of the Latitude, that Star riſeth not at all in our Horizon, and ſo of all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find, every Day in the year, at what time any of the Planets cometh to the South.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, bring the moving Meridian to 12 of the Clock and 20 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, the Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> and there keep it faſt, and then find the Sign and Degree that the Planet is in at that time, and then turn the whole upper Plain until that Sign and degree come to the moving Meridian placed at 12 of the Clock 20 degrees, and there keep them both faſt together, and then look in the Circle of Months for the Day you deſire to know the time of that Planets coming to the South, and right againſt that day in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, you will ſee at what of the Clock that Planet comes to the South.</p>
               <p>So ♄ <hi>Saturn's</hi> place or Longitude in the Ecliptick the 15 day of <hi>March,</hi> being 8 degrees 56 minutes of ♑ <hi>Capricorn,</hi> if you turn the whole upper moving Sphere until that Sign and degree in the Ecliptick come to the Meridian placed at 12 of the Clock 20 degrees, and there hold them both faſt together, and then right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the 15 day ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, it will appear that ♄ <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> cometh to the South at 6 of the Clock 20 minutes in the morning; and ♃ <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s place or Longitude in the Ecliptick the 15 day of <hi>March,</hi> being 14 degrees 3 minutes, in ♒ <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> cometh to the South at 8 of the Clock 46 Minutes paſt in the Morning; and the ſame day <hi>Mars</hi> being in 3 degrees 4 minutes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64660:12"/> of ♓ <hi>Piſces,</hi> cometh to the South at 10 of the Clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ♀ <hi>Venus</hi> the ſame day being in 18 degrees 50 minutes of ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> cometh to the South at 2 of the Clock 46 minutes in the Afternoon; and ☿ <hi>Mercury</hi> being then in 8 degrees 46 minutes of ♒ <hi>Aquarius,</hi> cometh to the South at 8 of the Clock 46 minutes paſt in the Morning: and the ſame day <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                  <hi>Luna</hi> being in 19 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 22 minutes of ♋ <hi>Cancer,</hi> cometh to the South at 7 of the Clock 21 minutes paſt in the Afternoon, allowing 2 minutes in the Ecliptick for each hour to be added to the place of the Moon, ſo here was added 14 minutes; <hi>Note,</hi> if the day whereon you deſire to know when the Star cometh to the South be in the Eaſt Semicircle, they are Morning hours; or if they be in the Weſt Semicircle, they are Afternoon hours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find the true Diſtance of the Moon's Motion from the Sun.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, by the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> find the Moon's place in the Ecliptick, then bring the moving Meridian to 12 hours and 20 degrees, the Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> and then bring the Moon's place in the Ecliptick alſo to that Meridian; and there hold them both faſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and then in the Circle of Months find the day you deſire to know, at what hour the Moon cometh to the Meridian, and right againſt that day you will find the hour of the Moon's then coming to the South.</p>
               <p>So the 17 day of <hi>March,</hi> the Moon being in 18 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo,</hi> being the moving Meridian to 12 hours and 20 degrees, the Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> then turn the whole upper Sphere until the Moon's place in the Ecliptick alſo come to that Meridian, and there keep them both faſt together, and then in the Circle of Months you will find right againſt the 17 day of <hi>March</hi> 9 hours 13 minutes in the Afternoon, which is the time of the Moon's coming to the South that day, alwayes in work remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring when you have found 9 hours to allow two Minutes for each hour, which here is 18 Minutes, which 18 minutes in the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, at the Rate of 4 minutes for a degree, is 4 degrees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64660:13"/> joyned to 18 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo</hi> the Moon's place maketh 22½ degrees, which is the true place that the Moon is then in; which brought to the Index placed at 12 hours and 20 degrees as before, and there kept faſt right againſt the 17 day of <hi>March</hi> will appear 9 of the Clock 13 minuts paſt in the afternoon, which is now the direct true time of the Moon's coming to the South.</p>
               <p>Note, On the lower fixed plain in this Inſtrument, are placed 3 hour-Circles, the outwardmoſt with 24 hours at ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> is to meaſure the right Aſcenſion in time; the middle hour-Circle, which I call ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle beginning at 12 a Clock and 20 degrees longitude, is proper for the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> to meaſure the hour of the day or night; the third, next the Equinoctial, is to meaſure time from the general or firſt Aſtronomical Meridian according to the diſtance betwixt the Sun or Stars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To find the longitude, by knowing when any of the fixed Stars cometh to the South.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, you muſt obſerve, that by this projection in the lower fixed plain repreſenting the Terreſtrial Globe, at one ſingle certain point take in the Equinoctial, there is ſet and placed 360 degrees with 12 of the Clock at noon in the next hour-Circle, and ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> in the ſecond hour-Circle, and 24 hours in the outward hour-Circle, and this Meridian thus ſtated is the firſt Meridian of the World, and declareth the beginning and ending of all longitude; which formerly by Geographers hath been placed at ſeveral parts of the World, ſome aſſigning it to paſs through St. <hi>Michaels</hi> Iſland, one of the <hi>Azores,</hi> others will have it to paſs through <hi>Tenaref</hi> one of the <hi>Canary</hi> Iſlands, and ſome again will have it paſs by or through, the Weſtermoſt parts of <hi>Africa;</hi> all as yet grounding themſelves, from courſes, diſtances, departures, differences of latitude and longitude, found by expert skilful practical Navigators according to their Sea obſervations and reckonings; for I ſuppoſe there have been as yet but few Eclipſes obſerved to contradict the expert Navigators indeavours, who indeed deſerve the honour and thanks for the originals which built that demonſtrative Figure and Type
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64660:13"/> called the Terreſtrial Globe, and I ſuppoſe will in the future gain the like honour in this great matter, by practical proof confirming a true Meridian and Longitude properly and peculiarly belonging to each particular part and place upon the Terreſtrial Globe, being the moſt competent Judges grounding their knowledg upon their great Attempts and remote Diſcoveries, which others, not verſed in thoſe things, muſt come far ſhort off. Now Aſtronomically we ſay 360 degrees muſt be accounted for the beginning and ending of all Longitude, but we cannot place that Meridian upon the earth at pleaſure, for that is abſurd and improper; but Aſtronomically, by knowing the time of any of the fixed Stars coming to the South, and the place or Longitude of the Sun in the Ecliptick that day, the diſtance then indeed betwixt the Sun and Star reckoned in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, ſheweth both their reſpective right Aſcenſions and alſo the Longitude in degrees or time conteined betwixt them, by which means this Inſtrument will readily ſhew the true Meridian and Longitude in all places upon the Terreſtrial Globe, provided it be granted, that at every minute of Time in one place or other, the Sun and Stars are alwaies Riſing, Setting, and coming to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian (which is not to be denied) then I ſay, each particular Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian and Longitude, upon the Terreſtrial Globe, may undoubtedly be cleerly diſcovered: For if it were inquired at what Meridian and Longitude the City of <hi>London</hi> was truly ſeated, if we ſhould ſearch the Terreſtrial Globes they would ſhew us ſeveral Longitude, according to the ſeveral places, where they appointed the firſt Meridian to begin and end all Longitude, and ſo in effect will ſhew us juſt nothing; for indeed there is but one ſingle proper Meridian belonging to the City of <hi>London,</hi> or any other place whatſoever, which may as ſurely be pointed out and ſhewed which is it in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular by this Inſtrument, as any Aſtronomical Calculator can tell you the very Day, Hour, &amp; Minut of the Stars coming to the South, which many will affirm they can infallibly perform, and ſeveral Authors have already drawn out Tables to that purpoſe, ſome of which I can teſtify are exceeding well, true, and perfectly done and performed; but I have not obſerved that any of them, hath truly ſtated and diſcovered the Meridian properly belonging to the particular Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> or pointed out which or where it is; I ſuppoſe the reaſon hath been, becauſe they found the Longitude
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64660:14"/> of places upon the earth were variouſly affirmed, and therefore they medled with none of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To find exactly the True Meridian and Longitude of the City of</hi> London.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, by this Inſtrument to find the true Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> you muſt conſider the day of what month you will imploy for this ſervice, which day I then call the day of the Sun; then alwaies bring the day of the Sun to 360 degrees, the beginning and ending of all Longitude, then take notice of any of the fixed Stars placed upon the upper moving Plain in this Inſtrument, and bring the moving Index to cut that Star, and in the outward hour-Circle you will find the hour and minute of that Stars coming to the South, when the day of the Sun ſtandeth at 360 degrees in the Equinoctial, which on the ſame day of the Sun will ſhew one and the ſame hour and minute, for the Stars being South in all the particular Longituds of the World; and ſo that hour, common to all Longituds, cannot diſtinguiſh the particular Meridian of any of them, but this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from that ground will ſhew each proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of all places upon the Terreſtrial Globe which cannot be removed or altred; for, if you count in the lower hour-Circle placed next the Equinoctial, 1 hour, 2 hours, 3 hours, 4 hours <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the diurnal motion, untill you bring the day of the Sun to ſuch an hour as right againſt it will ſtand the hour and minute in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, anſwerable and equal to the hour firſt found in the outward Circle conteining 24 hours a Natural day, at which time the day of the Sun was firſt brought to 360 degrees in the Equinoctial, and ſo the hour of the Star was that day one and the ſame in all Longitudes: but now (I ſay) if the day of the Sun be turned to ſo many hours and minuts in the lower hour-Circle that then againſt the ſame day of the Sun in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle there appear the hours and minutes equal to the hours and minutes firſt found in the outward Circle of 24 hours, I ſay, the Star pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed will then ſtand right againſt the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of the place deſired, and cannot poſſibly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64660:14"/> be removed or conſtrained to ſtand againſt any other Meridian or Longitude, but that which properly and particularly belongeth to that one ſingle part, point, or place upon the Terreſtrial Globe.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example. The firſt of <hi>April,</hi> I demand how the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> may be found and diſcovered, by this Inſtrument.</head>
                  <p>BRing the firſt day of <hi>April</hi> to 360 degrees, which I now call the day of the Sun, then find on the upper plain or Sphere the fixed Star called the <hi>Lyons Tayl,</hi> and thereon place the moving Meridian or Index, and then in the outward hour-Circle it will ſhew that Star cometh to the South at 10 a clock 13 minutes in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, which is the common hour for all Meridians in the World for that day; therefore now turn about the upper moving Plain or Sphere untill the firſt day of <hi>April</hi> the day of the Sun come to 8 hours 52 minutes in the lowermoſt hour-Circle, and then right againſt the ſame hour and day of the Sun in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle you will then find 10 a Clock 13 minutes at night equal to the hour firſt found in the outward hour-Circle, and ſo the Star called the <hi>Lyons Tayl</hi> will now ſtand exactly againſt 20 degrees in the Equinoctial, placed upon the fixed plain at 10 a Clock 13 minutes at night, which is the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> which cannot poſſibly be removed, changed, or altred, and was never truly found or thus ſtated by any Man before.</p>
                  <p>So in like manner, if you will the ſame firſt day of <hi>April</hi> imploy the fixed Star called <hi>Hidra's Heart,</hi> to find the true Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London,</hi> bring again the firſt day of <hi>April</hi> the day of the Sun as before to 360 degrees, and then place the moving Meridian upon that Star, and in the outward hour-Circle it will ſhew 7 a Clock 52 minutes; therefore now turn the day of the Sun to 6 hours 32 minutes in the lowermoſt hour-Circle, and then right againſt that in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle you will find again 7 a Clock
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64660:15"/> 52 minutes, and then you will find <hi>Hidra's Heart,</hi> will ſtand again directly right againſt 20 degrees, the proper Meridian and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of <hi>London</hi> as before at 7 a Clock and 52 minutes.</p>
                  <p>So in like manner if you will the ſame firſt day of <hi>Aprill</hi> imploy the Star called <hi>Virgin Spik</hi> bring the day of the Sun to 360 degrees and place the moving Meridian upon the Star, which will then in the outward hour Circle ſhew 11 a Clock 48 minuts, therefore now turn the day of the Sun to 10 hours 28 minuts, and at the ſame time right againſt that, in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, you will find 11 a Clock 48 minutes at night, and then the <hi>Virgin Spike</hi> will ſtand right againſt 20 degrees, the true Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London</hi> as before, and ſo in the ſame manner you may imploy any of the fixed Stars which you think convenient, and they will all affirm the true, proper, and particular Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London</hi> is directly 20 degrees, which cannot be removed, altred, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by any Man; and ſo being at any place or point upon the Terreſtrial Globe, by this Inſtrument, and the ſame Rule, you may find the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude of that place, which cannot be removed, altred, or denied by any one.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> at the Sun's Setting. Example.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the tenth day of <hi>April</hi> it be required to find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> at the ſetting of the Sun; bring the longeſt Meridian of the moving Horizon to 360 degrees the firſt Index of the world, and there keep it faſt, then turn the upper moving Sphere until the place of the Sun, being then the firſt minute of ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> come to the edg of the Horizon in the Weſt Semicircle of the Inſtrument; then bring the moving Meridian or <hi>Index</hi> to the place of the Sun, which <hi>Index</hi> will then at the ſame time in the Circle of dayes and months cut or ſhew the 10 day of <hi>April</hi> the day of the Sun; and now the Inſtrument thus ſtated, keep all the <hi>Indexe</hi>s and Horizon unaltered, and then turn
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64660:15"/> the whole upper moving Sphere, until that <hi>Index</hi> which cuts the day and place of the Sun come to 360 degrees, the firſt Meridian, and then the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon in the outward hour-Circle will cut 4 hours, which is the diſtance that day betwixt the Sun when he is on the Meridian, and the time of his ſetting when he is in the Horizon, and ſo continues at the ſame diſtance, for that day, upon all Meridians and Longitudes until the Sun, by the force of <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> is carried round about the world; Therefore now again turn the whole moving Sphere unaltered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Diurnal motion, until the <hi>Index</hi> at the day of the Sun cut in the innermoſt hour-Circle 5 hours 40 minutes, and then at the ſame time the ſame <hi>Index</hi> will alſo cut in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle 7 of the Clock in the Afternoon, the time of Sun ſetting, which was alſo the firſt diſtance cut in the outward hour-Circle; and then the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon will ſtay at 20 degrees, the true Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be removed, altered, or contradicted, and was never before found, known, or truly ſtated by any man until Now: and by the ſame Rule and Directions, being in any part of the world, we can as truly and exactly find the proper and particular Meridian and Longitude belonging to that place, as we have now ſetled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a true, proper, and particular Meridian and Longitude, not to be changed, removed, or altered for the City of <hi>London,</hi> which was never known or found before, confirmed both by the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Star, and Setting of the Sun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>THE THIRD WAY. To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London:</hi> at the Sun's Riſing.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the ſame tenth day of <hi>April</hi> it be required to find the true Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> at the Sun's Riſing; bring the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon to 360 degrees, the firſt Meridian as before, and there keep it faſt; then turn the upper moving Sphere, until the place of the Sun, being now the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64660:16"/> firſt minute of ♉ <hi>Taurus,</hi> come to the edg of the Horizon in the Eaſt Semicircle of the Inſtrument; then bring the moving Meridian or <hi>Index</hi> to the place of the Sun, which will then alſo cut the tenth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Circle of Months, which is now the day of the Sun; and ſo the Inſtrument thus ſtated, keep all the <hi>Indexes</hi> and Horizon unaltered; and now being it is Sun Riſing, turn the whole moving upper Sphere, until the <hi>Index</hi> which cuts the day and place of the Sun to 180 degrees, or 12 of the Clock at night, and then the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon will ſhew in the outward hour-Circle 7 hours, which is the diſtance being upon the firſt Meridian Now at 180 degrees 12 of the Clock at Night, which is the diſtance of the Sun that day betwixt the time when he's upon the Meridian, and riſeth in the Horizon, round about the world in all reſpective Meridians and Longitudes; Therefore now turn again the whole moving Sphere, according to his Diurnal Motion, until the <hi>Index</hi> at the day of the Sun in the innermoſt hour-Circle, cut 3 Hours 40 minutes, and then the ſame <hi>Index</hi> in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle, will ſhew 5 of the Clock the time of Sun Riſing, and the longeſt <hi>Index</hi> of the Horizon at the ſame time will ſtay again at 20 degrees as before, the true Meridian and Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> confirmed by three ſeveral wayes, and cannot be removed or altered to any other point, which point of Longitude was never found before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>THE FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RTH WAY. To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> by the Moon when ſhe cometh to the South.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the 11 day of <hi>May,</hi> the Moon being then in 2 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo,</hi> it were required to ſhew then the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London;</hi> firſt bring one Index in the Circle of Months to the 11th day of <hi>May</hi> the day of the Sun, then bring another Index to the 25 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo,</hi> the Moons place that day, and then the diſtance betwixt thoſe Indexes will appear in the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial to be 88 degrees, which in time is 5 a Clock 52 minutes;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64660:16"/> therefore now turn the whole moving upper Sphere, keeping the two Indexes unaltred, and bring the Index placed at the day of the Sun to 360 the firſt Meridian and begining and ending of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, and then the Index of the Moon, in the Equinoctial on the fixed Plain, will ſhew 88 degrees which is 5 hours 32 minutes in time: but in regard the Moon for this diſtance of time muſt have 2 minutes allowed for each hour, take with a pair of compaſſes 15 degrees of the fixed Equinoctial, and then ſet one foot in 88 degrees, and turn over the compaſſes untill they come to 360 degrees, and count how many times they are turned over which here will appear to be 6 times, therefore at 2 minutes for an hour, is 12 minutes, which added to 5 hours 52 minuts maketh 6 a Clock 4 minutes agreeing with Mr. <hi>Wings</hi> calculation, within 2 minutes; with 12 minutes add to 88 make 91 degrees, the true diſtance, the Moons Index now ſtanding there. Then the Indexces ſtill unaltred, turn the whole moving Sphere untill the Moons Index cometh to 6 a Clock 6 minutes, which will alſo cut 111 degrees in the Equinoctial, and then the Index of the Sun will then ſtay again at 20 degrees the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> as before, which cannot be removed, altred or contradicted by any one. And thus hath the true Longitude of <hi>London</hi> been confirmed by four ſeveral waies to be directly 20 degrees and no more, no Man having before now ever diſcovered what it was, and ſo by the ſame Rule, may the true Longitude of any part of the world be ſpeedily found.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>ANOTHER WAY. To find the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London</hi> by the Moon when ſhe cometh to the South.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe the eleventh day of <hi>May,</hi> the Moon being then in 25 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo,</hi> it were required to find the true Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the City of <hi>London;</hi> Firſt bring the 11th day of <hi>May</hi> now the day of the Sun to 360 degrees the firſt Meridian, and turn the Index to 25 degrees of ♌ <hi>Leo</hi> the Moon's place, that day, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64660:17"/> then the diſtance betwixt the Sun and the Moon will appear, in the Equinoctial upon the fixed Plain, to be 88 degrees, and in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hour-Circle 5 a Clock 52 minutes; but now in regard the Moon muſt be allowed 2 minutes for each hour to be added to this diſtance take 15 degrees with a pair of Compaſſes out of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial and ſet one foot in 88 degrees, and you will find you may turn them over neer fix times before you come to 360 degrees the firſt Meridian, therefore you muſt allow 12 minutes which is 3 degrees more in the Equinoctial, and the Moons Index muſt now ſtand at 91 degrees in the Equinoctial, and then in the outward hour-Circle will now ſhew 6 a Clock 4 minutes. Therefore now, keeping the Moons Index unaltred, turn the whole moving Sphere, untill the Index of the Moon cut in ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle to 6 a Clock 6 minutes in the morning, and then the 11th day of <hi>May</hi> the day of the Sun will ſtand right againſt 20 degrees in the Equinoctial, again the true Longitude of the City of <hi>London,</hi> as before, which cannot be altred or contradicted by any one And thus we have ſtated the true Longitude of <hi>London</hi> four ſeveral wayes to be directly 20 degrees and no more; which was not known or diſcovered before this time by any Man.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Note, the outward hour-Circle alwaies ſheweth the Suns diſtance from the Star, from the Horizon, or from the Moon in hours and minutes, and the Equinoctial ſheweth the diſtance in degrees.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And the Innermoſt hour-Circle ſheweth how many hours and minutes you may turn the day of the Sun or the place of the Moon.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And ♈ <hi>Aries</hi> hour-Circle in the middle alwaies in his own accompt ſheweth the ſame hour with the outward hour-Circle, and ſo determineth the hour of the day proper for that Latitude and Longitude which you are at.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64660:17"/>
               <head>Two ſeveral Queſtions by finding the Moon South to know what Meridian you are at.</head>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>The firſt Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>THe 10th day of <hi>June</hi> 1665 three Men being at Sea, the firſt Man had the Moon South at 6 hours 18 minutes; the ſecond Man, at 6 hours 29 minutes; and the third Man had the Moon South at 6 hours 32 minutes. I demand what Meridian and Longitude each of thoſe Men were then at?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, the 10th day of <hi>June,</hi> you may then readily find that the Sun is then in 29 degrees of ♊ <hi>Gemini</hi> at 20 degrees the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of <hi>London,</hi> and the Moon at that time in 3 degrees 50 minutes of ♎ <hi>Libra;</hi> therefore now ſet one Index to the 10th day of <hi>June</hi> the day of the Sun, and the ſame Index in the Ecliptick will then cut 29 degrees of ♊ <hi>Gemini,</hi> the place of the Sun: then lay the other Index on 3 degrees 50 minutes of ♎ <hi>Libra,</hi> the place of the Moon, and with the Indexes unaltred turn the upper Sphere untill the Index of the Sun cut 20 degrees the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> and the diſtance betwixt the two Indexes in the Equinoctial will be 94½ degrees which is 6 hours 18 minutes, the firſt Man's hour of having the Moon South: but the Index of the Moon then in the Equinoctial will alſo cut 115 degrees, the firſt Man's Meridian and Longitude that he was at.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The ſecond Man having the Moon South at 6 hours 29 minuts.</head>
                     <p>THE Indexes remaining as before turn the upper Sphere untill the Index of the Moon come to 20 degrees the Longitude of <hi>London;</hi> but now in regard there muſt be allowed 2 minutes for an hour for the Moons depreſſion, which is 12 minutes, therefore turn
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64660:18"/> back the Index of the Moon 3 degrees, and then turn again the moving upper Sphere untill the Index of the Moon cut 20 degrees, the Longitude of <hi>London;</hi> and the Index of the Sun will then cut 6 hours 29 minutes: ſo the ſecond Man had the Moon South at 20 degrees the Meridian of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The third Man having the Moon South at 6 hours 32 minutes.</head>
                     <p>THE Indexes not altred from the laſt propoſition, turn the upper Sphere untill the Index of the Moon come to 320 degrees, but now having 3 hours difference, allowing 2 minutes for an hour, turn back the Index of the Moon 1½ degree, and then turn again the upper Sphere untill the Index of the Moon cut 320 degrees, and then the Index of the Sun will cut 6 hours 32 minutes: ſo the third Man had the Moon South at the Meridian and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of 320 degrees.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>The Second Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>THe 17th day of <hi>June</hi> 1665 five Men being at Sea, the Moon then at the full at 10 a Clock 24 minuts paſt in the morning, the Sun in the 6 degree of ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> and the Moon in the 6 degree of ♑ <hi>Capricorn</hi> South at 22 a Clock, at 224 degrees the firſt Man's Meridian and Longitude; but the Second Man hath the Moon South at 12 minutes after 12 a Clock; the third Man 24 minutes after 12; the fourth Man 28 minutes after 12; and the fifth Man 34 minutes after 12 a Clock. I demand, what Meridian and Longitude each of theſe particular Men were then at?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, lay the Index one end on the 17th day of <hi>June</hi> which will then alſo cut 6 degrees of ♋ <hi>Cancer</hi> the Suns place, and the other end will then cut 6 degrees of ♑ <hi>Capricorn</hi> the Moons place, then move the upper Sphere untill the Suns end of the Index cut 10
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64660:20"/> a Clock 24 minutes paſt in the morning, the time of full Moon, and the Moon's end will then cut 224 degrees in the Equinoctial, which is the firſt Man's Longitude at 12 a Clock; then allowing 2 minutes for each 15 degrees, or one hour of time for the Moon's depreſſion, you will then firſt find that betwixt 224 degrees and 134 degrees is contained 90 degrees, which is 6 hours of time; now allowing 2 minutes for each hours depreſſion, in all 12 minutes, which is 3 degrees, turn the upper Sphere, the Index unaltred, untill the Moons end come to 134 degrees then 3 degrees allowed for depreſſion maketh exactly 12 a Clock 12 minutes paſt: So the ſecond Man's Longitude muſt be 134 degrees at that time and place. The third Man having the Moon South 24 minutes after 12 a Clock, allowing 2 minutes depreſſion for each hour, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that his Meridian and Longitude, when he hath the Moon South, muſt be 44 degrees: becauſe the diſtance betwixt 44 degrees and 224 degrees in the Equinoctial is 180 degrees, or 12 hours, and then 24 minutes which is 6 degrees allowed for depreſſion maketh 24 minutes after 12 a Clock: ſo the third Man muſt have the Moon South at the Meridian and Longitude of 44 degrees. The fourth Man had the Moon South at 20 degrees 28 minutes after 12 a Clock, becauſe the diſtance betwixt 20 degrees and 224 degrees in the Equinoctial is 204 degrees or 13 hours 9 minutes: therefore allowing 2 minutes depreſſion for an hour maketh 28 minutes after 12 a Clock: ſo the fourth Man, had the Moon South at 20 degrees the Meridian and Longitude of <hi>London.</hi> The fifth Man had the Moon South at 334 degrees 34 minutes after 12 a Clock, becauſe the diſtance according to the Diurnal motion betwixt 334 degrees and 224 degrees is 250 degrees or 17 hours, allowing 2 minutes depreſſion for an hour, maketh 34 minutes: ſo the fifth Man had the Moon South at 334 degrees 34 minutes after 12 a Clock; which is all that was required.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Rule and reaſon for turning the upper Shere is from 360 degrees.</head>
                     <p>THE rule is to ſee how many hours and minutes the Sun can be turned from the firſt point of ♈ <hi>Aries,</hi> before t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Star can come to be South: and the reaſon is becauſe the Star cannot be South but at one time at one Meridian.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:64660:21"/>
                     <head>To cut the Horizons for all Latituds.</head>
                     <p>UPon a peice of paſtboard draw two lines Squarewiſe, that is perpendicular to each other, and let the longeſt line be the diameter of the upper Sphere, and the ſhorter the perpendicular, the Latitude from the Center of the Index, by which means, from the Center where the two lines croſs each other there is got or found 3 points; now find the Center to thoſe 3 points, and ſtrike an arch, and cut out by that arch the Horizon required.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 6. l. 28. for <hi>pannage</hi> read <hi>parallels,</hi> p. 8. l. 17. for <hi>Terreſtrial r. Celeſtial,</hi> p. 11. l. 26. for <hi>contein r. count,</hi> p. 17. l. 1. for <hi>all Altines r. all Times,</hi> p. 24. l. 27. for <hi>firſt Index r. firſt Meridian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64660:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
